{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Statement:  A large number of people in ward X of the city are diagnosed to be suffering from a fatal malaria type.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe city municipal authority should take immediate steps to carry out extensive fumigation in ward X.\nThe people in the area should be advised to take steps to avoid mosquito bites.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, prevention from mosquitoes and elimination of mosquitoes are two ways to prevent malaria. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  Severe drought is reported to have set in several parts of the country.\nCourses of Action:\n\nGovernment should immediately make arrangement for providing financial assistance to those affected.\nFood, water and fodder should immediately be sent to all these areas to save the people and cattle.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In the break-out of a natural calamity, the basic duty of the government becomes to provide the basic amenities essential to save the lives of people and cattle. Providing financial assistance to all would put undue burden on the country's resources. So, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Since its launching in 1981, Vayudoot has so far accumulated losses amounting to Rs 153 crore.\nCourses of Action:\n\nVayudoot should be directed to reduce wasteful expenditure and to increase passenger fare.\nAn amount of about Rs 300 crore should be provided to Vayudoot to make the airliner economically viable.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, for better economic gain, losses should be reduced and income increased. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Exporters in the capital are alleging that commercial banks are violating a Reserve Bank of India directive to operate a post shipment export credit denominated in foreign currency at international rates from January this year.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe officers concerned in the commercial banks are to be suspended.\nThe RBI should be asked to stop giving such directives to commercial banks.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement mentions that the commercial banks violate a directive issued by the RBI. The remedy is only to make the banks implement the Act. So, none of the courses follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  A large number of people die every year due to drinking polluted water during the summer.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should make adequate arrangements to provide safe drinking water to all its citizens.\nThe people should be educated about the dangers of drinking polluted water.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The situation demands creating awareness among people about the dangers of drinking polluted water so that they themselves refrain from the same, and at the same time taking steps to provide safe drinking water. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  Most of those who study in premier engineering colleges in India migrate to developed nations for better prospects in their professional pursuits.\nCourses of Action:\n\nAll the students joining these colleges should be asked to sign a bond at the time of admission to the effect that they will remain in India at least for ten years after they complete education.\nAll those students who desire to settle in the developed nations should be asked to pay entire cost of their education which the government subsidises.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, no student can be bound to live and work in the country against his wish. So, I does not follow. However, it is quite right to recover the extra benefits awarded to students if they do not serve their own country. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  There is an unprecedented increase in migration of villagers to urban areas as repeated crop failure has put them into precarious financial situation.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe villagers should be provided with alternate source of income in their villages which will make them stay put.\nThe migrated villagers should be provided with jobs in the urban areas to help them survive.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, increased migration would add to the burden on city's infrastructure. So, attempts should be made to make the villagers feel comfortable in the villages itself. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  As stated in the recent census report the female to male ratio is alarmingly low.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should conduct another census to verify the results.\nThe government should immediately issue orders to all the departments to encourage people to improve the ratio.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A census is always conducted with the utmost precision, leaving chances of only negligible differences. So, I does not follow. Further, the ratio can be improved by creating awareness among the masses and abolishing female foeticide. Thus, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Four districts in State A have been experiencing severe drought for the last three years resulting into exodus of people from these districts.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should immediately start food for work programme in the district to put a halt to the exodus.\nThe government should make since efforts to provide drinking/potable water to these districts", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The exodus can be stopped by providing the people conditions conducive to living. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  If the retired Professors of the same Institutes are also invited to deliberate on restructuring of the organisation, their contribution may be beneficial to the Institute.\nCourses of Action:\n\nManagement may seek opinion of the employees before calling retired professors.\nManagement should involve experienced people for the systematic restructuring of the organisation.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the statement stresses that the contribution of retired Professors shall be beneficial. This means that these people's experience regarding working of the organisation is helpful. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The sale of a particular product has gone down considerably causing great concern to the company.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe company should make a proper study of rival products in the market.\nThe price of the product should be reduced and quality improved.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, a study of rival products in the market will help assess the cause for the lowering down of sales and then a suitable action can be taken. Thus, only I follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Asian Development Bank has approved a $285 million loan to finance a project to construct coal ports by Paradip and Madras Port Trusts.\nCourses of Action:\n\nIndia should use financial assistance from other international financial organisations to develop such ports in other places.\nIndia should not seek such financial assistance from the international financial agencies.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, such projects shall be an asset and a source of income to the country later on. So, course I shall follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  Doordarshan is concerned about the quality of its programmes particularly in view of stiff competition it is facing from STAR and other satellite TV channels and is contemplating various measures to attract talent for its programmes.\nCourses of Action:\n\nIn an effort to attract talent, the Doordarshan has decided to revise its fee structure for the artists.\nThe fee structure should not be revised until other electronic media also revise it.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the decision to revise its fee structure for artists is taken by Doordarshan as a remedy to the challenging problem that had arisen before it. It cannot wait till other media take action. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Minister said that the teachers are still not familiarised with the need, importance and meaning of population education in the higher education system. They are not even clearly aware about their role and responsibilities in the population education programme.\nCourses of Action:\n\nPopulation education programme should be included in the college curriculum.\nOrientation programme should be conducted for teachers on population education", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the statement stresses on teachers' lack of awareness and knowledge in population education and as such the best remedy would be to guide them in this field through orientation programmes. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  A recent study shows that children below five die in the cities of the developing countries mainly from diarrhoea and parasitic intestinal worms.\nCourses of Action:\n\nGovernments of the developing countries should take adequate measures to improve the hygienic conditions in the cities.\nChildren below five years in the cities of the developing countries need to be kept under periodic medical check-up.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the two diseases mentioned are caused by unhygienic conditions. So, improving the hygienic conditions is a step towards their eradication. Also, periodic medical check-up will help timely detection of the disease and hence a proper treatment. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The kharif crops have been affected by the insects for consecutive three years in the district and the farmers harvested less than fifty percent of produce during these years.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe farmers should seek measures to control the attack of insects to protect their crops next year.\nThe Government should increase the support price of kharif crops considerably to protect the economic interests of farmers.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the problem demands taking extra care and adequate precautions to protect crops from insects and extending help to farmers to prevent them from incurring huge losses. Thus, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The car dealer found that there was a tremendous response for the new XYZ's car-booking with long queues of people complaining about the duration of business hours and arrangements.\nCourses of Action:\n\nPeople should make their arrangement of lunch and snacks while going for car XYZ's booking and be ready to spend several hours.\nArrangement should be made for more booking desks and increased business hours to serve more people in less time.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Seeing the tremendous response, the dealer must make suitable arrangements and deploy more personnel to take care of customers so that they don't have to wait excessively long for booking. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The State Government has decided to declare 'Kala Azar' as a notifiable disease under the Epidemics Act. Family members or neighbours of the patient are liable to be punished in case they did not inform the State authorities.\nCourses of Action:\n\nEfforts should be made to effectively implement the Act.\nThe cases of punishment should be propagated through mass media so that more people become aware of the stern actions.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The Act is aimed at eradication of the disease and so it needs to be proclaimed and promoted. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Chairman stressed the need for making education system more flexible and regretted that the curriculum has not been revised in keeping with the pace of the changes taking place.\nCourses of Action:\n\nCurriculum should be reviewed and revised periodically.\nSystem of education should be made more flexible.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the situation demands making the education system more flexible and changing it periodically according to the needs of the time. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Central Bureau of Investigation receives the complaint of an officer taking bribe to do the duty he is supposed to.\nCourses of Action:\n\nCBI should try to catch the officer red-handed and then take a strict action against him.\nCBI should wait for some more complaints about the officer to be sure about the matter.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, one complaint is enough for a wrong doing. This should be confirmed by catching the guilty red-handed and then strict action taken against him. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Indian electronic component industry venturing into the West European markets faces tough competition from the Japanese.\nCourses of Action:\n\nIndia should search for other international markets for its products.\nIndia should improve the quality of the electronic components to compete with the Japanese in capturing these markets.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An escapist's attitude does not help much. The need is to compete and emerge successful. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Orissa and Andhra Pradesh have agreed in principle to set up a joint control board for better control, management and productivity of several inter-state multipurpose projects.\nCourses of Action:\n\nOther neighbouring states should set up such control boards.\nThe proposed control board should not be allowed to function as such joint boards are always ineffective.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The effectiveness of such Control Boards is established by the fact that Orissa and A.P. have agreed to it for better control of its multipurpose projects. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Government has decided not to provide financial support to voluntary organisations from next Five Year Plan and has communicated that all such organisations should raise funds to meet their financial needs.\nCourses of Action:\n\nVoluntary organisations should collaborate with foreign agencies.\nThey should explore other sources of financial support.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The problem arising is shortage of funds. So, alternative sources of financial support need to be worked out first. Thus, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The availability of imported fruits has increased in the indigenous market and so the demand for indigenous fruits has been decreased.\nCourses of Action:\n\nTo help the indigenous producers of fruits, the Government should impose high import duty on these fruits, even if these are not of good quality.\nThe fruit vendors should stop selling imported fruits. So that the demand for indigenous fruits would be increased.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The ideas suggested in both I and II represent unfair means to cut competition. The correct way would be to devise methods and techniques such that the indigenous producers could produce better quality fruits and make them available in the market at prices comparable with those of the imported ones. Hence, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  There has been an unprecedented increase in the number of successful candidates in this year's School Leaving Certificate Examination.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should make arrangements to increase number of seats of intermediate courses in existing colleges.\nThe government should take active steps to open new colleges to accommodate all these successful candidates.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The increase may not be a permanent one. So, it's better not to open new colleges but increase seats in the existing colleges. So, only I follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  On an average, about twenty people are run over by trains and die every day while crossing the railway tracks through the level crossing.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe railway authorities should be instructed to close all the level crossings.\nThose who are found crossing the tracks, when the gates are closed, should be fined heavily", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The accidents can clearly be prevented by barring people from crossing the tracks when the gates are closed, So, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Majority of the students in many schools do not pass in the final examination.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThese schools should be closed down as these have become unproductive.\nThe teachers of these schools should immediately be retrenched.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, the situation demands that efforts be made to remove the lackenings in the present system of education and adequate measures be taken to improve the performance of students. Harsh measures as those given in I and II, won't help. So, none of the given courses follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  In spite of the Principal's repeated warnings, a child was caught exploding crackers secretly in the school.\nCourses of Action:\n\nAll the crackers should be taken away from the child and he should be threatened not to do it again.\nThe child should be severely punished for his wrong act.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the act has been repeated despite various warnings, so course I would only be another warning and would not help. Severe punishment to set example for him and others is inevitable. Thus, course II shall follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  It is necessary to adopt suitable measures to prevent repetition of bad debts by learning from the past experiences of mounting non-performing assets of banks.\nCourses of Action:\n\nBefore granting loan to customers their eligibility for loan should be evaluated strictly.\nTo ensure the payment of instalments of loan, the work, for which loan was granted, should be supervised minutely on regular basis.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "To ensure that debts taken are repaid promptly, the customer's requirements and future prospects ought to be studied and their work constantly checked. Thus, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  A very large number of students have failed in the final high school examination due to faulty questions in one of the subjects.\nCourses of Action:\n\nAll the students who have failed in the subject should be allowed to take supplementary examination.\nAll those who are responsible for the error should be suspended and an enquiry should be initiated to find out the facts.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "There being faulty questions in the examination paper is a blunder on the part of school management and students should not be made to suffer on account of this. Thus, a re-test should be organised for the students and those responsible for the error be penalised to prevent reoccurrence of such mistake in the future. Hence, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  A large number of engineering graduates in the country are not in a position to have gainful employment at present and the number of such engineers is likely to grow in the future.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should launch attractive employment generation schemes and encourage these graduates to opt for such schemes to use their expertise and knowledge effectively.\nThis happened due to proliferation of engineering colleges in the country and thereby lowered the quality of the engineering graduates. Those colleges which are not equipped to impart quality education should be closed down.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The emphasis should be not on the Government putting all the engineering graduates to jobs but on the colleges producing not 'degree-holders' but real technical minds which could compete well for gainful employment. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Every year, at the beginning or at the end of the monsoons, we have some cases of conjunctivitis, but this year, it seems to be a major epidemic, witnessed after nearly four years.\nCourses of Action:\n\nPrecautionary measures should be taken after every four years to check this epidemic.\nPeople should be advised to drink boiled water during rainy season.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The disease occurs at the end of monsoons every year. So, precautionary measures every four years shall not help. The second course of action shall be a preventive measure. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Every year large number of devotees dies due to severe cold on their way to the shrine located at the top of the mountain range.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe devotees should be discouraged to visit the shrine without having proper warm clothes and other amenities.\nThe government should provide warm clothes and shelter to all the devotees visiting the shrine.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the problem can be solved by warning the devotees of the excessive cold at the shrine. So, only I follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  There has been an unprecedented increase in the number of requests for berths in most of the long distance trains during the current holiday season.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe railway authority should immediately increase the capacity in each of these trains by attaching additional coaches.\nThe people seeking accommodation should be advised to make their travel plan after the holiday.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "People cannot be deprived of going to a certain destination merely for lack of berths. Instead it is the duty of the railway authority to accommodate all the bookings by all means. So, only I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Finance Minister submits his resignation a month before the new budget is to be presented in the Parliament.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe resignation should be accepted and another person should be appointed as the Finance Minister.\nThe resignation should not be accepted.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, an already working Finance Minister shall know better all the plans and resources of the Government and he alone can present a suitable budget. So, course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  A large number of people visiting India from country X have been tested positive for carrying viruses of a killer disease.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government of India should immediately put a complete ban on people coming to India from country X including those Indians who are settled in country X.\nThe government of India should immediately set up detection centres at all its airports and seaports to identify and quarantine those who are tested positive.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the non-infected persons should not be debarred from visiting India. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  There has been less than forty percent voter turnout in the recent assembly elections.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe election commission should cancel the entire election process as the votes cast are not adequate to represent people.\nThe election commission should take away the voting rights of those who did not exercise their rights.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Re-election would demand repeated expenses and following course II would reduce the voter base permanently. Instead, awareness should be created among the people to use their right to vote effectively. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Most of the development plans develop in papers only.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe in-charges should be instructed to supervise the field-work regularly.\nThe supply of paper to such departments should be cut short.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, proper supervision alone can see the development in practice. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The vegetable traders feel that the prices of onion will again go up shortly in the State 'P'\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe 'P' State Government should purchase and store sufficient quantity of onion in advance to control prices.\nThe 'F' State Government should make available network of fair price shops for the sale of onions during the period of shortage.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, both the courses of action seem appropriate to prevent black-marketing in case of shortage. Hence, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  It is reported that though Vitamin E present in fresh fruits and vegetables is beneficial for human body, capsule Vitamin E does not have the same effect on human body.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe sale of capsule Vitamin E should be banned.\nPeople should be encouraged to take fresh fruits and vegetables to meet the body's requirement of Vitamin E.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement implies that capsule Vitamin E does not function so effectively as natural Vitamin E. Since no negative effect of capsule Vitamin E is mentioned, so I does not follow. Hence, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Youngsters are often found staring at obscene posters.\nCourses of Action:\n\nChildren should be punished and penalized if they are found doing so.\nAny display of such material should be banned.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Bad things attract more and punishment after the act has been committed is no remedy. The act should be prevented. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  One of the problems facing the food processing industry is the irregular supply of raw material. The producers of raw material are not getting a reasonable price.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should regulate the supply of raw material to other industries also.\nThe government should announce an attractive package to ensure regular supply of raw material for food processing industry.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, to remedy the problem of food processing industry, a regular supply of raw material should be ensured. So, course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Committee has criticized the Institute for its failure to implement a dozen of regular programmes despite an increase in the staff strength and not drawing up a firm action plan for studies and research.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe broad objectives of the Institute should be redefined to implement a practical action plan.\nThe Institute should give a report on reasons for not having implemented the planned programmes.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The problem is that despite an increase in staff strength, the Institute has failed in its objective of implementing its plan. So, either there should be reasons for the lackening or the plans are a failure and must be revised for practical implementation. Thus, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  India has been continuously experiencing military threats from its neighbouring countries.\nCourses of Action:\n\nIndia should engage into an all out war to stop the nagging threats.\nIndia should get the neighbours into a serious dialogue to reduce the tension at its borders.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, war is the last resort. First, peaceful talks and negotiations should be indulged in, to settle the issues of dispute. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  As many as ten coaches of a passenger train have derailed and blocked both pairs of the railway tracks.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe railway authorities should immediately send men and equipment to the spot to clear the railway tracks.\nAll the trains running in both the directions should be diverted to other routes.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The situation demands first diverting other trains to different routes so as to avert any accident, and then clearing the tracks as soon as possible. Thus, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  There has been a significant drop in the water level of all the lakes supplying water to the city.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe water supply authority should impose a partial cut in supply to tackle the situation.\nThe government should appeal to all the residents through mass media for minimal use of water.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The situation can be tackled by periodic cuts in supply, and urging people to conserve water. So both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The police department has come under a cloud with recent revelations that at least two senior police officials are suspected to have been involved in the illegal sale of a large quantity of weapons from the state police armoury.\nCourses of Action:\n\nA thorough investigation should be ordered by the State Government to bring out all those who are involved into the illegal sale of arms.\nState police armoury should be kept under Central Government's control.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the situation demands finding out the real culprits first. So, only I follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  Financial stringency prevented the State Government from paying salaries to its employees since April this year.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe State Government should immediately curtail the staff strength at least by 30%.\nThe State Government should reduce wasteful expenditure and arrange to pay the salaries of its employees.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, curtailing of the staff strength will only increase the panic and discontent, and the satisfaction of the employees is a must. So, the Government should arrange for payment of wages. Thus, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The cinema halls are incurring heavy losses these days as people prefer to watch movies in home on TV than to visit cinema halls.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe cinema halls should be demolished and residential multi-storey buildings should be constructed there.\nThe cinema halls should be converted into shopping malls.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Doing away with cinema halls is no solution. Hence, none of the courses follows. Instead, certain incentives and promotional schemes should be awarded to cinema hall owners so that they could manage to draw in crowds."}, {"question": "Statement:  Duty free technology parks where foreign firms can manufacture electronic hardware components are proposed to be established at various places in the country.\nCourses of Action:\n\nGovernment should immediately implement the proposal to augment the foreign currency reserve by exporting the products.\nGovernment should not implement the proposal as it will hinder indigenous production of hardware components.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The step discussed in the statement would surely give a boost to hardware industry and help our country to stand apart in this field. Thus, only I follows."}]]}